<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="92"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Table of Contents                                    Page No.


                 Acronyms                                                                             5




                 Introduction                                                                         7



                 Harmonized National R&D Agenda (HNRDA)                                               8

                 Framework



                 SECTION I               National Integrated Basic                                    10

                                         Research Agenda (NIBRA)



                 SECTION II              Health                                                       16



                 SECTION III             Agriculture, Aquatic and Natural                             26

                                         Resources (AANR)




                 SECTION IV              Industry, Energy and Emerging                                33

                                         Technology



                 SECTION V               Disaster Risk Reduction and                                  40

                                         Climate Change Adaptation

                                         (DRR & CCA)













                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Table of Contents                                   Page No.

                 Annexes: Roadmaps                                                                   46

                                                    NIBRA
                 Annex 1     TUBIG Program (Tubig ay Buhayin at Ingatan)                             47
                             SAPAT Program (Saganang Pagkain Para sa Lahat)
                 Annex 2     LIKAS Program (Likas Yaman sa Kalusugan)                                48
                             ALERT Program (Alternative Energy Research Trends)
                 Annex 3     SAKLAW Program (Saklolo sa Lawa)                                        49
                 Annex 4     ATIN Program (Ang Tinig Natin)                                          50

                                                    Health
                 Annex 5     National Unified Health Research Agenda                                 51

                          Agriculture, Aquatic and Natural Resources (AANR)
                 Annex 6     Crops:  Abaca | Banana                                                  53
                 Annex 7     Crops:  Coconut | Coffee                                                54
                 Annex 8     Crops:  Legumes - Mungbean | Peanut                                     55
                 Annex 9     Crops:  Mango | Rice                                                    56
                 Annex 10    Crops:  Rootcrops - Sweet Potato                                        57
                             Crops:  Sugarcane
                 Annex 11    Crops:  Tropical Fruits - Citrus | Durian                               58
                 Annex 12    Crops:  Tropical Fruits - Papaya | Pineapple                            59
                 Annex 13    Crops:  Tropical Fruits - Pummelo                                       60
                             Crops:  Vegetables
                 Annex 14    Livestock:  Dairy | Duck                                                61
                 Annex 15    Livestock:  Dairy Goat | Slaughter Goat                                 62
                 Annex 16    Livestock:  Native Chicken | Native Pig                                 63
                 Annex 17    Livestock:  Swine | Feed Resources                                      64
                 Annex 18    Aquatic:  Inland - Aquafeeds | Mangrove Crab                            65
                 Annex 19    Aquatic:  Inland - Milkfish | Mussel                                    66
                 Annex 20    Aquatic:  Inland - Shrimp | Tilapia                                     67
                 Annex 21    Aquatic:  Marine - Abalone | Blue Swimming Crab                         68
                 Annex 22    Aquatic:  Marine - Oyster | Sardines                                    69
                 Annex 23    Aquatic:  Marine - Sea Cucumber | Seaweeds                              70
                 Annex 24    Aquatic:  Marine - Tuna                                                 71
                             Forestry & Natural Resources:  Bamboo
                 Annex 25    Forestry & Natural Resources:  Cacao | Industrial Tree Plantation       72
                 Annex 26    Forestry & Natural Resources:  Rubber                                   73
                             Environmental Services:  Biodiversity
                 Annex 27    Environmental Services:  Corals                                         74
                 Annex 28    Environmental Services:  Climate Change | Watershed                     75






                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Table of Contents                                   Page No.


                               Industry, Energy and Emerging Technology
                 Annex       Competitive Industries:  ICT, Electronics and Semiconductor             76
                 29-30
                 Annex 31    Delivery of Social Services:  DRR/CCA                                   78

                 Annex       Delivery of Social Services:  Space Technology Application              79
                  32-34
                 Annex       Intelligent Transportation Solutions                                    82
                  35-39
                 Annex       Renewable Energy and Energy Storage Solutions                           87
                  40-41

                        Disaster Risk Reduction and Climate Change Adaptation
                 Annex 42    DRR-CCA R&D Roadmap                                                     89
                 Annex 43    PAGASA Roadmap                                                          90








































                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Acronyms




                     Acronym                                     Definition

                 AANR               Agriculture, Aquatic and Natural Resources
                 AIS                Automatic identification system

                 ALERT Program      Alternative Energy Research Trends Program
                 ATIN Program       Ang Tinig Natin Program

                 BMI                Body mass index
                 CCTV               Closed-circuit television

                 CHED               Commission on Higher Education
                 CVD                Cardiovascular disease

                 DNA                Deoxyribonucleic acid
                 DOH                Department of Health

                 DOST               Department of Science and Technology
                 DRR & CCA          Disaster Risk Reduction and Climate Change Adaptation

                 ENGP               Enhanced National Greening Program

                 FGD                Focused Group Discussion
                 GIT                Gastrointestinal tract
                 GNSS               Global navigation satellite system

                 GUT                Genitourinary tract

                 H2S                Hydrogen sulfide
                 HAB                Harmful algal bloom
                 HNRDA              Harmonized National Research and Development Agenda

                                    Human immunodeficiency virus and acquired immunodeficiency
                 HIV AIDS
                                    syndrome
                 HIW                High-Impact Weather
                 HYV                High yielding variety

                 ICT                Information and Communication Technology
                 IEC                Information Education and Communication

                 ITS                Intelligent transportation system
                 IVM                Integrated vector management

                 LIKAS Program      Likas Yaman sa Kalusugan Program
                 MSME               Micro, small and medium enterprise

                 NGA                National Government Agency





                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[NIBRA              National Integrated Basic Research Agenda
                 NIH-UPM            National Institutes of Health, University of the Philippines Manila

                 NRCP               National Research Council of the Philippines
                 NRDC               National Research and Development Conference

                 NUHRA              National Unified Health Research Agenda
                                    Philippine Council for Agriculture, Aquatic and Natural Resources
                 PCAARRD
                                    Research and Development
                                    Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services
                 PAGASA
                                    Administration
                 PCHRD              Philippine Council for Health Research and Development
                                    Philippine Council for Industry, Energy and Emerging Technology
                 PCIEERD
                                    Research and Development
                 PES                Payment for Environmental Services
                 PHIVOLCS           Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology

                 PNHRS              Philippine National Health Research System
                 PWD                Persons with disabilities

                 PTC                Positive Train Control
                 PUV                Public Utility Vehicle

                 QPF                Quantitative Precipitation Forecasting
                 R&D                Research and Development

                 RE                 Renewable Energy
                 RFID               Radio Frequency Identification

                 RUTF               Ready to use therapeutic food
                 SAKLAW Program  Saklolo sa Lawa Program

                 SAPAT Program      Saganang Pagkain Para sa Lahat Program
                 SCP                Solar Power Concentrators

                 SDG                Sustainable Development Goal
                 SHC                Solar heating and cooling

                 STA                Space Technology Application
                 T2DM               Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus

                 TUBIG Program      Tubig ay Buhayin at Ingatan Program
                 UAV                Unmanned Aerial Vehicles

                 UN                 United Nations
                 WSN                Wireless Sensor Network

                 XDP                X-linked Dystonia-Parkinsonism Syndrome






                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Introduction



               The  DOST,  in  consultation  with  government  and  private  research  and  development
               institutions, the academe, industry and other concerned agencies, prepared the Harmonized
               National R&D Agenda (HNRDA) 2017-2022 to ensure that results of S&T endeavors are geared
               towards and are utilized in areas of maximum economic and social benefit for the people. The
               formulation of the HNRDA is in line with the DOST’s mandate of providing central direction,
               leadership and coordination of the scientific and technological efforts in the country.

               The HNRDA is aligned with AmBisyon Natin 2040: matatag, maginhawa at panatag na buhay
               para  sa  lahat.  It  has  three  pillars:  Malasakit  (enhancing  the  social  fabric),  Pagbabago
               (reducing inequality) and Kaunlaran (increasing potential growth). AmBisyon Natin 2040 and
               the three pillars form the foundation for more inclusive growth, a high-trust and resilient
               society and a globally competitive knowledge economy.

                                                          st
               On 21 October 2016, the DOST hosted the 1 National R&D Conference (NRDC) to harmonize
               the country’s research and development priorities and align them with the thrusts of the
               current administration. Comments and recommendations raised during the 1st NRDC were
               considered in the final version of the HNRDA which was presented to stakeholders during the
               2nd National R&D Conference on 15 February 2017.

               One of the outcomes identified in the Philippine Development Plan 2017-2022 is to increase
               the  country's  potential  growth  by  building  the  foundation  for  a  globally  competitive
               knowledge economy where accelerated technology adoption and stimulated innovation are
               envisioned to be achieved. The HNRDA, therefore, articulates our national priorities and will

               serve  as  guide  for  public  investment  in  R&D  while  ensuring  a  cohesive  convergence  and
               integration of R&D efforts towards the shared goal of inclusive socio-economic growth and a
               better life for Filipinos.

               The  HNRDA  is  organized  into  5  sectors:    Basic  Research;  Agriculture  Aquatic  and  Natural
               Resources; Health; Industry, Energy and Emerging Technology; and Disaster Risk Reduction
               and  Climate  Change  Adaptation.  The  Agenda  was  formulated  by  the  National  Research
               Council  of  the  Philippines  (NRCP),  Philippine  Council  for  Agriculture,  Aquatic  and  Natural
               Resources Research and Development (PCAARRD), Philippine Council for Health Research and
               Development  (PCHRD),  Philippine  Council  for  Industry,  Energy  and  Emerging  Technology
               Research and Development (PCIEERD), Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology

               (PHIVOLCS),  and  Philippine  Atmospheric,  Geophysical  and  Astronomical  Services
               Administration (PAGASA) in cooperation with stakeholders in the respective sectors.









                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[The Harmonized National Research and Development Agenda (HNRDA) is divided into five
                  (5) sectors. It is aligned with AmBisyon Natin 2040, and is founded on the three pillars of
                                          Malasakit, Pagbabago and Kaunlaran.






















                                                                                                                                              HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  8]]></page><page Index="9"/><page Index="10"><![CDATA[HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  9]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  9]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[SECTION I



                         National Integrated Basic Research Agenda


                                             (NIBRA) 2017-2022


               The  National  Research  Council  of  the  Philippines  (NRCP),  a  collegial  body  of  over  four
               thousand  researchers,  scientists,  and  experts,  is  mandated  to  promote  and  support
                                                                                th
               fundamental and basic research in the country as provided in the 9  Philippine Legislature Act
               No. 4120 passed on 8 December 1933.  It is likewise mandated to provide advice on problems
               and issues of national interest.

               Along this line, the NRCP supports research that is directed primarily towards developing a
               new and fuller scientific knowledge or understanding of any subject which may or may not
               have practical applications. Basic research results from intellectual curiosity aimed at proving
               the unknown, or it may seek new knowledge required for practical application in the future
               (Ref:  Science Act of 1958 as amended by RA 3589).

               For 2017-2022, the NRCP’s National Integrated Basic Research Agenda (NIBRA) will prioritize
               fundamental research in support of the Philippine Development Plan, the National Security
               Plan, and the Science for Change Program led by the Department of Science and Technology.
               It has six issue-based NIBRA programs, namely:

                    A.  Water Security – TUBIG Program (Tubig ay Buhayin at Ingatan)
                    B.  Food and Nutrition Security – SAPAT Program (Saganang Pagkain Para sa Lahat)
                    C.  Health Sufficiency – LIKAS Program (Likas Yaman sa Kalusugan)
                    D.  Clean Energy – ALERT Program (Alternative Energy Research Trends)
                    E.  Sustainable Community – SAKLAW Program (Saklolo sa Lawa)
                    F.  Inclusive Nation-building – ATIN program (Ang Tinig Natin)

               Among these six, the top three priority areas for 2017-2019 are SAKLAW, ATIN, and LIKAS
               Programs.  Outputs of NRCP-funded research are journal and scholarly publications, policy
               advisories, patent applications, and products used for community and public engagements
               such as books, manuals, monographs, among others.

               The NIBRA is a product of a series of consultations and forums which started in 2016.  The
               thirteen disciplinal Divisions of NRCP generated their respective basic research agenda.  These
               are  the  Divisions  of  Governmental,  Educational  and  International  Policies  (Division  1),
               Mathematical Sciences (Division II), Medical Sciences (Division III), Pharmaceutical Sciences
               (Division  IV),  Biological  Sciences  (Division  V),  Agriculture  and  Forestry  (Division  VI),
               Engineering  and  Industrial  Research  (Division  VII),  Social  Sciences  (Division  VIII),  Physics
               (Division IX), Chemical Sciences (Division X), Humanities (Division XI), Earth and Space Sciences
               (Division XII), and Veterinary Medicine (Division XIII).






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  10]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[The divisions’ basic research agenda were further harmonized by the NRCP clusters before the
               NIBRA was approved by the Governing Board and confirmed by the General Membership
               Assembly.


               A.  Water Security

                    TUBIG Program (Tubig ay Buhayin at Ingatan)
                    1.  Watershed studies
                        a.  Biological, chemical and physical characterization
                        b.  Water supply stress index
                        c.  Population growth impacts on water resource availability
                    2.  Water quality, accessibility and availability
                        a.  Pollutants/contaminants (surface and ground waters)
                        b.  Analysis of historical flows, sediment and toxicity loads of lakes and rivers
                        c.  Weather modification for increasing water supplies in special localized areas

                    Priorities for 2017-2019
                    Ensuring an adequate supply of quality water that is accessible to a growing population
                    is TUBIG Program’s priority for 2017-2019.  Specific topics include:
                    a.  Characterization of water resources (ground water)
                    b.  Impact of various climate change scenarios on water supply

                    Priorities for 2020-2022
                    Studies on rivers, reservoirs, dams and other surface water resources will be the priority
                    for 2020-2022 which will include:
                    a.  Characterization of water resources (surface water)
                    b.  Impact of various climate change scenarios on water supply

               B.  Food and Nutrition Security
                    SAPAT Program (Saganang Pagkain Para sa Lahat)
                    1.  Biodiversity studies
                        a.  Biological Pollution
                        b.  Biology and population dynamics of pests, diseases, and natural enemies
                        c.  Taxonomy of flora and fauna
                        d.  Environmental scanning of physical marine and terrestrial resources
                            (taxonomy, systematics, ecology)
                        e.  Genetic analysis (biochemical, cytogenetics, molecular)
                        f.  Taxonomy of eco-friendly species (e.g. arthropods and microorganisms) for
                            Integrated Pest Management
                        g.  Exploring allelopathic potentials of indigenous botanicals
                    2.  Food safety
                        a.  Safety analysis of food supplements and cosmeceuticals in the market







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  11]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[b.  Livestock and poultry diseases (epidemiological studies, re-emerging and
                            emerging diseases)
                        c.  Diseases and pathogens of important crops
                        d.  Identification and characterization of food/feed contaminants
                        e.  Epidemiology of food- and feed-borne contaminants

                     Priorities for 2017-2019
                     Basic research along two strands is SAPAT Program’s priority in the next three years.
                     a.  Taxonomy and systematics of flora and fauna for food. Specific topics include
                        genetic analysis, morphological analysis and allelopathic analysis.
                     b.  Safety analysis of cosmeceuticals and food supplements. Specific topics include
                        epidemiology, microbiology, chemical analysis, cost-benefit and socio-economic
                        studies.

                     Priorities for 2020-2022
                     There will be the same priorities in 2020-2022, but focus will be on:
                     a.  Bio-ecology studies of flora and fauna for food
                     b.  Safety analysis of raw and processed food products

               C.  Health Sufficiency
                    LIKAS Program (Likas Yaman sa Kalusugan)
                    1.  Fundamental Studies on Potential Sources of Natural Products
                        a.  Bioprospecting (e.g. marine organisms for biomedical use)
                        b.  Bioinformatics
                        c.  Characterization and structure elucidation of plants or foods/food components
                        d.  Pharmacogenomics and toxicogenomics
                    2.  Basic Veterinary Studies
                        a.  Economically important animal diseases and those transmitted to humans
                        b.  Characterization, isolation and bioassay of novel antimicrobial compounds
                            from indigenous sources and plant species
                        c.  Herbal veterinary pharmacopeia
                        d.  Identification and characterization of zoonotic diseases
                    3.  Social Dimensions on Health
                        a.  Filipino perceptions and concepts on health
                        b.  Herbal and folkloric medicine
                        c.  Models for good governance in health management

                     Priority for 2017-2019
                     Fundamental studies on potential sources of natural products in various ecosystems
                     such as marine sediments, rivers, and rare environments (e.g. caves, mangroves, mined
                     out areas, mesophotic reefs) is the priority of the LIKAS Program.  This primarily includes
                     bio-prospecting studies for medicinal applications with focus on marine ecosystems in
                     2017-2019.





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  12]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[For the basic veterinary studies, priority will be on zoonotic diseases.

                     Priority for 2020-2022
                     The same type of studies will be prioritized in 2020-2022, but focus will be on the other
                     types  of  ecosystems,  specifically  rare  environments  as  potential  sources  of  natural
                     products for medicinal use.

                     For basic veterinary studies, research will focus on the other economically important
                     diseases.

               D.  Clean Energy
                    ALERT Program (Alternative Energy Research Trends)

                    1.  Alternative Energy
                        a.  Identification and characterization of alternative sources of energy (wind,
                            solar, biofuels, hydro)

                   Priority for 2017-2019
                   In  the  next  three  years,  NRCP  will  support  the  conduct  of  resource  assessments  of
                   potential alternative sources of energy.

                   Priority for 2020-2022
                   By  2020,  priority  will  be  on  conduct  of  commercial  viability  studies  of  the  potential
                   alternative sources of energy identified from previous studies.

               E.  Sustainable Communities

                    SAKLAW Program (Saklolo sa Lawa)
                    1.  Vulnerable Ecosystems
                        a.  Lakes, rivers, and wetlands
                        b.  Oceans and marine studies
                        c.  Soil science
                        d.  Carrying capacity models of ecosystems
                        e.  Environmental scanning of physical marine and terrestrial resources
                        f.  Endangered species
                        g.  Economic valuation of ecosystems, natural capital, and cost-benefit analyses
                        h.  Evaluation of adaptive socio-ecological systems in a changing environment
                        i.   Assessment studies on the resource sustainability of various ecosystems
                        j.   Models and frameworks for enhancing adaptive capacities of vulnerable
                            communities
                    2.  Data Analytics of Natural Phenomena
                        a.  Database of pollutants present in abandoned mined out areas (terrestrial and
                            aquatic)






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  13]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[b.  Computational and numerical modelling and simulations for ecological
                            processes
                        c.  Simulations for applications in physical and life sciences, and in complex
                            systems
                        d.  Regional climate modelling and sensitivity analysis
                    3.  Environment and Anthropogenic Activities
                        a.  Geogenic health hazards
                        b.  Processes in heavy metals sequestration from mine tailings, agriculture, farms,
                            etc.
                        c.  Impact studies of anthropogenic activities on the environment (e.g. mining and
                            resource extractive industries)
                        d.  All-systems risk modelling for DRR/CCA
                        e.  Human dimensions research on climate change (drivers, impact, responses,
                            adaptive capacities)
                        f.  Risk assessment of mining wastes and effluents
                        g.  Bioremediation studies

                   Priorities for 2017-2019
                   SAKLAW Program is the topmost priority of NRCP for 2017-2019 and it will focus on the
                   following topics:
                   a.  Lake assessment studies --  carrying capacity models and metrics; water quality
                       parameters and baseline studies;  resource assessment and valuation; resource
                       utilization and management;  socio-economic and policy studies. Both big lakes and
                       small lakes in the country will be included in the program.
                   b.  Coastal vulnerabilities  --  risk assessment; geohazard mapping; adaptive capacities;
                       marine geology;  computational and numerical modelling.  The focus will be on
                       DENR-identified highly vulnerable ecosystems.
                   c.  Resource extractive industries – fundamental studies of all types of mining areas

                   Priority for 2020-2022
                   Similar types of basic research will be supported but focus will be on rivers and other
                   bodies of water, and other ecosystems.


               F.  Inclusive Nation-Building
                    ATIN program (Ang Tinig Natin)
                    1.  Data Collection and Analysis of Social Phenomena
                        a.  Computational and numerical modelling and simulations for social processes
                        b.  Indigenous knowledge systems and practices on DRR and CCA
                        c.  Gender in nation-building and DRR/CCA
                    2.  Documentation of Indigenous Knowledge
                        a.  Documentation of traditional health practices in the Philippines
                        b.  Extant cultural heritage of ethnolinguistic groups
                        c.  Dictionary of cultural metaphors





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  14]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[d.  Retrieval and documentation of indigenous technology in Filipino expressive
                            culture
                        e.  Documentation of indigenous sustainable farming, fishing, and aquaculture
                            practices
                        f.  Early human life and civilization in the Philippines
                    3.  Education
                        a.  Pedagogies in Philippine educational system
                        b.  Mathematics, language, music in indigenous Filipino expressive culture
                        c.  K12 studies
                    4.  National Security and Sovereignty
                        a.  Peace studies and conflict resolution
                        b.  Sovereignty issues
                        c.  Human security (community, political, health, economic, environmental,
                            personal)
                    5.  Arts, History and Culture
                        a.  Extant cultural heritage of ethnolinguistic groups
                        b.  Filipinnovation in music, theatre, dance, literature, performing arts
                        c.  Codification of endangered Philippine languages

                   Priorities for 2017-2019
                   ATIN  Program  is  the  second  priority  for  2017-2019.    Among  the  five  themes  above-
                   mentioned, the topmost priority will be:
                   a.  Documentation of indigenous knowledge (art and art forms, practices, technologies,
                       early human life and civilization in the Philippines)
                   b.  National security and sovereignty  --  to include studies on internal conflict and
                       peace, human security as well as maritime and geopolitical studies.

                   Priority for 2020-2022
                   For 2020-2022, the same topics will be supported in addition to new developments that
                   may arise.

                   For all the NIBRA programs, basic research on the cross-cutting themes of gender, KAPS
                   (knowledge, attitude, practices, skills), policy studies, valuation and cost benefit-analysis,
                   impact studies, and DRR/CCA dimensions will be considered.


                   The NIBRA Roadmaps are on pages 47-50.
                   For details, visit http://www.nrcp.dost.gov.ph/













                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  15]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[SECTION II



                                                      HEALTH

                               Research and Development Agenda

                                                   2017 – 2022



               Republic Act No. 10532 or the Philippine National Health Research System (PNHRS) Act of
               2013 recognizes and mandates the Philippine Council for Health Research and Development
               (PCHRD-DOST) as the national coordinating body for health research in the country.  Together
               with the PNHRS core agencies: Department of Health (DOH), Commission on Higher Education
               (CHED), and National Institutes of Health – University of the Philippines Manila (NIH-UPM),
               the National Unified Health Research Agenda (NUHRA) was developed. The NUHRA serves
               the following purposes: it is the national roadmap for health research in the Philippines; it
               provides focus and direction for health research and development efforts; it guides policy
               makers, funding and donor agencies and researchers; it provides evidence-based solutions to
               pressing  health  problems;  and  it  serves  as  basis  for  maximizing  resource  utilization  and
               minimizing duplication of research efforts.

               The  research  priorities  for  health  research  and  development  (R&D)  is  a  product  of
               consultations with experts and stakeholders from the private and public sectors including
               other line agencies of government, academe, and industry. Consultations were done through
               meetings,  workshops  and  focused  group  discussions  (FGDs).  The  research  priority  setting
               activities were guided by the DOST’s S&T thrusts, emerging and re-emerging health concerns
               and other national and global development concerns. The health R&D priorities comprise the
                                                     1
               health S&T component of the NUHRA.


                                                                                                  2
                      RESEARCH PRIORITIES for HEALTH RESEARCH and DEVELOPMENT

               A.  Diagnostics
               B.  Drug discovery and development
               C.  Functional foods


               1  Apart from the health S&T component of the NUHRA 2017-2022, the said document is also inclusive of other
               themes that cover diseases of globalization, urbanization, and industrialization, i.e., mental health, accidents
               and injuries, and substance abuse.
               2  Although not specifically reflected in this document, priority health research topics address the triple burden
               of  disease,  with  diseases  of  globalization,  urbanization,  and  industrialization  covered  in  the  management/
               supportive care for such conditions under biomedical devices including some in the areas of diagnostics, omic
               technologies, and climate change adaptation.




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  16]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[D.  Hospital equipment and biomedical devices
               E.  Information and communication technology for health
               F.  Dengue
               G.  Nutrition and food quality and safety
               H.  Disaster risk reduction
               I.  Climate Change Adaptation
               J.  Omic technologies for health (Platform technology across research priorities)

               A. Diagnostics

                     Development  of  diagnostics  for  early  detection  and/or  prediction  of  disease  and
                       mortality, utilizing existing technologies and/or novel technology. Such technology will
                       also look at the genetic or biological markers associated with lifestyle diseases like
                       diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular diseases and cancer.


                   1.  Priority diseases:
                       a.  Communicable diseases
                          •  Neglected Tropical diseases
                          •  Emerging infectious diseases
                          •  Organisms associated with Multi Drug Resistance
                          •  HIV AIDS
                          •  Genitourinary tract (GUT), Gastrointestinal tract (GIT) and Hepatitis
                          •  Respiratory diseases
                          •  Tuberculosis, all forms
                       b.  Non-communicable diseases
                          •  Malignant neoplasms, all sites
                          •  Neurodegenerative and mental health disorders
                          •  Metabolic Diseases, diabetes & other endocrine-related disorders
                          •  Autoimmune/immunologic diseases or deficiencies
                          •  Cerebrovascular disease
                          •  Diseases of the cardiovascular system

                   2.  Specific topics:
                       a. Point of care
                          •  Diagnostic test done at the time and place of patient care
                       b.  Screening / confirmatory / prognostic
                          •  Screening to detect early disease or risk factors for disease
                          •  Confirming the presence or absence of disease
                          •  Prognosticating and predicting the likely outcome of disease, susceptibility
                              and chances of recovery
                       c.  Technologies
                          •  Latex agglutination
                          •  Lateral flow assay/Dipstick
                          •  Isothermal technology





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  17]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[•  Biosensors/Chemical sensors
                          •  Nucleic Acid Testing
                          •  Immunochemistry
                          •  Lab-on-a-chip (microfluidics, paper technology, nanotechnology, aptamers or
                              a combination)
                          •  Immunoassay
                          •  Radio-labelled assays

                   Priorities for 2018
                       Proof of concept for screening, confirmatory and prognosis for 13 priority diseases
                       (tropical   diseases;  malignant  neoplasms;     emerging    infectious   diseases;
                       neurodegenerative and mental health disorders; diseases associated with multi-drug
                       resistance; metabolic diseases, diabetes and other endocrine-related diseases; auto-
                       immune/immunologic  diseases  and  deficiencies;  cerebrovascular;  diseases  of  the
                       cardiovascular system; GUT, GIT and hepatitis; respiratory; and tuberculosis)

                   Priorities for 2019-2022
                       Target identification and validation, prototype development, laboratory performance
                       testing, and field testing of diagnostic kits for 13 priority diseases.

               B.  Drug discovery and development
                      Development of standardized herbal drugs and discovery of new drugs from local
                        sources for development up to the pre-clinical stage. Drugs will be developed for:
                    1.  Infectious diseases
                        •  Bacterial infections (M. tuberculosis, Enterococcus faecium, S. aureus, Klebsiella
                            pneumoniae, Acinetobacter baumanii)
                        •  Viral diseases (e.g. dengue, influenza)
                        •  Fungal infections
                    2.  Non-communicable diseases
                        •  Lifestyle-related diseases (e.g. diabetes, cardiovascular diseases (CVDs), etc.)
                        •  Cancer (colon, breast, lung)
                        •  Respiratory diseases
                        •  Neurodegenerative diseases

                   Priorities for 2018
                          Cultural management/propagation of priority organisms
                          Development of standardized herbal drugs
                          o  Formulation of standardized herbal drugs for platelet enhancement related
                              to dengue, inflammation, diabetes, gout, hypertension
                          Pre-clinical drug development
                          o  Bioactive hits isolation from marine and terrestrial organisms for identified
                              priority diseases







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  18]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[  Development and/or validation of standard processes and protocols for various
                          stages of drug discovery and development

                   Priorities for 2019-2022
                         Cultural management/propagation of priority organisms
                         Development of standardized herbal drugs
                          o  Pre-clinical evaluation of standardized herbal drugs for platelet enhancement
                              related to dengue, inflammation, diabetes, gout, hypertension
                          o  Identification and screening of next set of priority plants for formulation for
                              identified priority diseases
                         Pre-clinical drug development
                          o  Lead optimization of candidates from marine and terrestrial organisms for
                              identified priority diseases
                         Development and/or validation of standard processes and protocols for various
                          stages of drug discovery and development

               C.  Functional Foods

                      Food  or  food  components  that  provide  health  benefits  beyond  basic  nutrient
                        function
                      Determination of health benefits and safety assessment of food or food components
                        in reducing risk for disease occurrence, specifically lifestyle related diseases such as
                        cardiovascular disease, diabetes, and cancer

                   1.  Priority Foods
                       a.  Local Fruits (guyabano, tiesa, mangosteen)
                       b.  Local Vegetables (malunggay, okra, saluyot)
                       c.  Rootcrops, tubers and starchy food (yacon, sago, sweet potato varieties, purple
                          yam)
                       d.  Rice (pigmented)
                       e.  Local berries (duhat, lipote, aratiles, bignay)
                       f.  Herbs and spices (tanglad, pandan, ginger e.g. turmeric)
                       g.  Nuts (pili)
                       h.  Seaweeds (lato, red seaweeds)
                       i.  Edible mushrooms

                   2.  Specific topics
                       a.  Characterization of food and food components
                       b.  Safety assessment
                       c.  Establishment of health benefits
                       d.  Product development

                   Priorities for 2018
                         Safety assessment of mangosteen, malunggay, sweet potato varieties, and ginger





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  19]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[  Characterization of guyabano (leaves, fruit, etc.) tiesa, yacon, sago, pili, lato, red
                          seaweed, and edible mushroom
                   Priorities for 2019-2022
                         Establishment of health benefits and product development of mangosteen,
                          malunggay, sweet potato varieties, and ginger
                         Safety assessment, establishment of health benefits and product development of
                          guyabano (leaves, fruit, etc.) tiesa, yacon, sago, pili, lato, red seaweed, and edible
                          mushroom
                         Characterization, safety assessment, establishment of health benefits, and
                          product development of okra, saluyot, purple yam, pigmented rice, duhat, lipote,
                          aratiles, bignay, tanglad, and pandan


               D.  Hospital Equipment and Biomedical Devices
                     Design and development of affordable, safe, and reliable hospital equipment and
                       biomedical devices

                   Specific topics
                   Priorities for 2018
                       Design and development of hospital equipment and biomedical devices for the
                       following:
                       •  Respiratory failure support
                       •  Artificial body part replacement (prosthesis)
                       •  Rehabilitation medicine
                       •  Minimally invasive surgical procedures
                       •  Eye health

                   Priorities for 2019-2022
                       Design and development of hospital equipment and biomedical devices for the
                       following:
                       •  Hemodialysis (consumables)
                       •  Orthopedic surgery
                       •  Post-operative care
                       •  Spinal disorders
                       •  Wound care
                       •  Primary health care
                       •  Persons with disabilities (PWD) assistive devices
                       •  Hospital waste management
                       •  Personal protective equipment

               E.  Information and Communication Technology (ICT) for Health
                     User-friendly ICT solutions to accelerate the gathering and processing of health and
                       related information for policymaking and delivery of quality health care services





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  20]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Specific topics
                   Priorities for 2018
                         Public health surveillance
                         Health intelligence system
                         ICT-enabled medical devices and services

                         Software and applications

                   Priorities for 2019-2022

                         Monitoring proximity to predict possible epidemics
                         Verbal autopsy system
                         Applications development for online nutrition services
                         Automatic body mass index (BMI) assessment

               F.  Dengue
                     Dengue R and D intends to reduce transmission of dengue and development of an
                       early warning system for the prediction of dengue outbreak.

                    Specific topics
                         Vector biology
                         Vector surveillance and integrated vector management (IVM)
                         Dengue case management
                         Dengue outbreak management

                   Priorities for 2018
                       Vector surveillance and IVM
                         Molecular characterization
                         Guidelines for the use of ovitraps
                         Insecticide resistance survey
                       Dengue outbreak response

                         Dengue outbreak prediction
                         Development of system for yearly monitoring of prevailing dengue serotypes

                   Priorities for 2019-2022
                       Vector surveillance and IVM

                         Epidemiological and molecular survey of mosquito borne viruses
                         Genome editing of Aedes aegypti
                         Gene silencing mosquito spray
                       Dengue outbreak response
                         Intensive profiling of dengue trends using rapid diagnostics






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  21]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[G. Nutrition and food quality and safety
                     Nutrition  research  seeks  to  address  the  nutrition  problems  in  the  country  i.e.,
                       micronutrient  and  macronutrient  deficiencies,  overnutrition,  and  nutrition  related
                       diseases, and to explore avenues and other opportunities that can be tapped, in order
                       to lessen if not stop these problems.
                     Food quality and safety refers to the assurance that food will not cause harm to the
                       consumer when prepared or eaten according to its intended use.

                   Specific topics
                         Food fortification
                          o  Fortified multi-nutrient growth mix products
                          o  Rice extrudate
                         Development/revision of nutrition tools and standards
                          o  Nutritional guidelines
                          o  Food exchange list
                          o  Body composition assessment
                         Nutritional assessment and monitoring
                          o  In-depth and correlation studies (dietary risk factors to non-communicable
                              diseases)
                          o  Nutrition surveys
                         Designing nutrition intervention programs
                          o  Nutrition delivery system for complementary feeding promotion
                         Food quality and safety
                          o  Enhancement of food composition database for dietary exposure assessment
                          o  Exposure assessment of selected nutrients, food contaminants, and food
                              additives in commonly consumed foods

               H.  Disaster Risk Reduction

                      Based on the Sendai Framework
                      Innovations which will reduce risks to health

                    Specific topics
                    Priorities for 2018
                         Innovations for emergency medical care services, water, sanitation, hygiene and
                          nutrition
                          o    technology development for search and rescue, triage and emergency

                               health
                          o    ready to use therapeutic food (RUTF)
                          o    food for emergencies
                          o    environmental health (water quality; waste disposal)

                         Psychosocial adaptation capacity of communities




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  22]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Priorities for 2019-2022
                         Intervention models to reduce prevalence of infectious diseases
                         Post disaster solutions to access health care services, e.g. maternal, newborn and
                          child  health,  sexual  and  reproductive  health,  food  security,  nutrition,  housing,
                          education
               I.  Health and Climate Change Adaptation
                       Covers  cross-cutting  research  on  climate  change  adaptation,  which  have  direct

                        implications on public health

                   Specific topics
                   Priorities for 2017-2022
                          Research relating to human health with hydrologic/meteorological information
                          Climate change sensitive diseases
                          Resilience studies at institutional, community and individual levels
                          Implementation science regarding existing tools and interventions on health and
                          climate change
                          Green health facilities

               J.  Omic Technologies for Health
                       Utilize molecular technology platforms in developing local technologies for the
                        development of personalized medicines, diagnostics, therapeutics as support to
                        health and clinical practice guidelines and policies

                          Priority diseases based on the top causes of mortality and morbidity (e.g. CVD)
                          malignant neoplasms, pneumonia and other chronic respiratory diseases
                          Prevalent emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases
                          Neurological/ Neurodegenerative/ mental health conditions
                          Disease conditions of special interest in the Philippines, e.g. X-linked dystonia-
                          parkinsonism syndrome (XDP)
                          Other applications / topics of national interest or significance

                    Specific topics
                          Omic Technologies for Health and Wellness
                          Bioinformatics and Systems Biology

                          Novel Technologies for Therapeutics
                          Biobanking, Data Mining and Population Studies for Human Health, Ethnicity and
                          Forensic Applications

               Priorities for 2018
                       Omic Technologies for Health and Wellness







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  23]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[  Omic research programs on neurological/ neurodegenerative/ mental Health
                            Conditions (susceptibility and drug response)
                          Validation of candidate genomic markers on susceptibility and drug response
                            for CVD and type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM)

                          Human host and viral markers of dengue severity (knowledge generation on
                            pathophysiological and molecular mechanisms of dengue severity)

                          Nutrigenomics

                       Bioinformatics and Systems Biology

                          Development of computational approaches and formulating bioinformatics
                            pipeline to study Filipino genomes
                          Data mining for lung or breast cancer tissues

                       Novel Technologies for Therapeutics
                            Development of molecular vehicles for targeted drug delivery

                       Biobanking, Data Mining and Population Studies for Human Health, Ethnicity and
                       Forensic Applications
                            Developing forensic methods used in criminal investigations, kinship analysis
                              and victim identification
                            Studies on Filipino DNA markers for forensic applications
                            Characterization of Filipino genomic variations (22 regional groups and 24
                              ethno-linguistic groups- sample collection)
                            Establishing a biobanking resource of Filipino samples and their associated
                              data (Genomic, Proteomic etc.)

                       Priorities for 2019-2022
                       Omics Technologies for Health and Wellness
                            Validation of candidate genomic markers on susceptibility and drug response
                              for Neurodegenerative/ Mental Health Diseases
                            Omic research programs on rare diseases in the Filipino population
                              (susceptibility and drug response)
                            Omic research programs on human host and infectious disease markers of
                              susceptibility, severity and therapeutic response
                            Nutrigenomics
                       Bioinformatics and Systems Biology
                            Developing the national capability for bioinformatics, chemoinformatics,
                              computational biology and big data analytics for the medical and health
                              sciences
                            Validation and testing of computational approaches and formulating
                              bioinformatics pipelines to study Filipino genome
                       Novel Technologies for Therapeutics






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  24]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[  Validation, pre-clinical and clinical testing of molecular vehicles for targeted
                              drug delivery
                       Biobanking, Data Mining and Population Studies for Human Health, Ethnicity and
                       Forensic Applications
                            Validation of use of omic technologies for forensics for the use in criminal
                              investigations, kinship analysis and victim identification
                            Validation of Filipino DNA markers for forensic applications

                            Data mining of Filipino genomic variations (22 regional groups and 24 ethno-
                              linguistic groups- sample collection)

                            Management of biobanking resource of Filipino samples and their associated
                              data (genomic, proteomic etc.)

               For further details about the NUHRA, visit www.pchrd.dost.gov.ph/















































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  25]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[SECTION III



                  AGRICULTURE, AQUATIC AND NATURAL RESOURCES

                                                      (AANR)


                               Research and Development Agenda

                                                   2017 – 2022



               The Harmonized National R&D Agenda in AANR (HNRDA-AANR) 2017-2022 is an integration
               of the existing R&D agenda of government agencies conducting R&D in AANR and inputs from
               various stakeholders.

               The  HNRDA-AANR  2017-2022  is  a  product  of  multi-sectoral  consultations.  Initially,  a
               Roundtable Consultation was conducted by the Philippine Council for Agriculture, Aquatic and
               Natural  Resources  Research  and  Development  (PCAARRD)  with  representatives  from
               government agencies performing R&D functions in AANR on October 13, 2016 at PCAARRD,
               Los Baños, Laguna. The output of the consultation, an initial draft agenda, was then presented
               during the National R&D Conference on October 21, 2016 held at Crowne Plaza Hotel Galleria,
               Quezon City. The conference was attended by representatives from government, the academe
               and private sector and civil society groups. The draft HNRDA-AANR was also presented to the
               Regional R&D Consortia during the Joint Regional R&D Consortium Chairpersons and Directors
               meeting held at PCAARRD on November 28, 2016. In addition, it was sent to heads of agencies
                                                                                           nd
               involved in R&D in AANR for validation, and further discussed during the 2  Round Table
               Consultation held on February 10, 2017 at PCAARRD.

               The  AANR  sector  supports  the  use  of  advanced  and  emerging  technologies  such  as
               biotechnology,  genomics,  bioinformatics,  nanotechnology,  nuclear  technology,  space
               technology, electronics and automation, and ICT as R&D tools to find S&T solutions to AANR
               problems or develop new products with significant potential impact to the sector.

               The sector supports organic agriculture, halal food production, food safety and traceability
               initiatives, and the development of genetically modified organisms as long as it is compliant
               with biosafety rules and regulations.

               The AANR sector also supports Farm Mechanization, as mandated by RA 10601, otherwise
               known as the Agricultural and Fisheries Mechanization Law, to modernize the sector and
               increase agricultural productivity, efficiency and competitiveness.






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  26]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Commodity Focus
                                AGRICULTURE                         AQUATIC               FORESTRY
                        Crops                Livestock
                 Abaca and other fiber   Livestock            Inland                Timber
                 crops                   - Swine              Mangrove crab         Tree plantations (e.g.
                 Coconut                 - Goat               Milkfish and other    yemane, falcata)
                 Rice                    - Sheep              brackishwater fishes
                 Corn and Other Grains   - Cattle (dairy and   (e.g. Kitang, Pompano)   Non-Timber
                 Fruit Crops              meat)               Mussel                Bamboo
                 -  Mango                - Carabao (dairy and   Tilapia and other   Rattan
                 -  Banana                meat)               freshwater fishes (e.g.   Sago
                 -  Other tropical fruits   -Rabbit           Goby/Pijango, Pigek)   Tiger grass
                   (e.g. durian,        Poultry               Shrimp                Vines and other non-
                   jackfruit, pummelo,   - Chicken (meat and   Aquafeeds            timber
                   papaya, pineapple,      egg)                                     Biodiversity
                   citrus)               - Duck (meat and     Marine                  * Ecosystem (e.g.
                 Legumes (e.g.             egg)               Abalone               mangrove, marine,
                 mungbean, peanut        - Quail              Blue Swimming Crab    freshwater)
                 and soybean)           Native animals        Cephalopods –           * Microbial
                 Natural Sources of Dye   - Chicken           cuttlefish, octopus,     * Flora and Fauna
                 Pili and Cashew         - Duck               squid                   * Ecotourism
                 Ornamentals (e.g.       - Swine              Oyster and other
                 cutflowers and foliage)   - Goat             shellfish
                 Medicinal Plants       Feed Resources        Sardines
                 Plantation Crops                             Sea cucumber
                 -  Cacao                                     Seaweeds
                 -  Coffee                                    Tuna
                 -  Oil Palm
                 -  Rubber
                 -  Sugarcane
                 Rootcrops (e.g. sweet
                 potato, cassava)
                 Sericulture and
                 Apiculture
                 Vegetables (e.g.
                 tomato, white potato,
                 mushroom)




                               RESEARCH PRIORITIES for AGRICULTURE, AQUATIC
                                        AND NATURAL RESOURCES (AANR)


               A.  Crops R&D Agenda
                    1.  Germplasm evaluation, conservation, utilization and management




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  27]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[2.  Varietal improvement and selection
                    3.  Production of good quality seeds and planting materials
                        a.  Development/optimization of seed production protocols
                        b.  Establishment of sustainable seed system

                    4.  Cultural Management Practices
                        a.  Soil health, nutrient and water management
                        b.  Development of biofertilizers and soil fertility enhancers
                        c.  Development of eco-friendly pest and disease management and control
                            strategies
                        d.  Development of crop disease diagnostic kits/techniques and disease
                            management protocols
                        e.  Organic Agriculture
                    5.  Crop production systems research
                        a.  Smart farming approaches
                        b.  Off-season production and cultivation
                        c.  Development of climate-resilient technologies
                        d.  Decision support systems
                    6.  Postharvest, processing and product development

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Breeding to develop improved crop varieties, including genomic studies to
                          improve yield and other economically important traits of crops
                         Development of good agricultural practices
                         Optimization of crop production protocols
                         Mapping/surveillance of pests and diseases, including emerging ones
                         Use of biologically-based approaches as well as nanotechnology in crop cultural
                          management (e.g. soil nutrient management, pest and disease management)
                         Product development from various crops

                   Priorities for 2020 onward
                         Multilocation trials of various technologies
                         Mass production of pest and disease resistant varieties of various crops
                         Roll out of various mature technologies

               B.  Livestock R&D Agenda

                    1.  Breed development and genetic improvement (for meat, dairy and draft)
                    2.  Reproductive biotechniques for priority livestock species
                    3.  Nutrition, feeds and feeding system
                    4.  Conservation and improvement of native animals
                    5.  Vaccine, biologics and diagnostics development
                    6.  Detection of chemical residues and anti-microbial resistance
                    7.  Production and management decision support systems





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  28]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[8.  Product development and processing

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Native Animals R&D Program
                         Application of genomics in breeding and selection
                         Improvement of cultural management protocols

                         Forage processing, development alternative feed ingredients and feeding
                          systems
                         Development of animal breed registry, diagnostic protocols and test kits,
                          traceability systems
                         Processing and product development

                   Priorities for 2020 onward
                         Development of quality standards for dairy products
                         Pilot testing and/or roll out of various technologies

               C.  Aquatic R&D Agenda
                    1.  Application of genomics in the study of diseases of aquatic species, improving fish
                        resistance to climate change; molecular phylogenetics; population genetics
                    2.  New cultivable species for culture
                    3.  Development/Refinement of culture systems (broodstock management, hatchery,
                        nursery, grow-out)
                    4.  Fish health, disease diagnostics and disease management
                    5.  Nutrition, feeds and feeding systems
                    6.  Postharvest handling, processing and new product development
                    7.  Mechanization and automated systems for feeding, water and culture management
                        and post production
                    8.  Fishkill warning and mitigation systems and environmental management for
                        sustainable aquaculture
                    9.  Management of fisheries

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Genetic studies and marker development, selective breeding
                         Bioinformatics analysis, population genomics
                         Improving fish health and nutrition, feeds and feeding systems for improved
                          production performance
                         Development/refinement and field testing of culture technologies on
                          economically important species
                         Biology, ecology and stock enhancement and population studies
                         Ecosystem based fisheries management
                         Postharvest handling and processing






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  29]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Priorities for 2020 onward
                         Pest and disease management/surveillance
                         Product development, including harnessing pharmaceutical and other uses of
                          aquatic species
                         Improving the management of fishery resources

                         Offshore fisheries and oceanography
                         Roll out of various technologies

               D.  Forestry R&D Agenda
                    The following agenda are in support of the government’s Enhanced National Greening
                    Program (ENGP):
                    1.  Development and sustainable management practices
                    2.  Development of high yielding varieties (HYVs) of priority timber species with
                        superior traits
                    3.  Production protocols for the propagation of quality timber and non-timber forest
                        planting materials
                    4.  Development of sustainable harvesting and postharvest techniques/technologies
                        and marketing strategies for timber and non-timber forest species/products

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Genomics assisted breeding for economically important traits of forest species
                         Germplasm conservation and management of selected indigenous tree species
                         Assessment of forest genetic materials of different tree species
                         Pest and disease control
                         Establishment of nursery facility for plantation trees

                   Priorities for 2020 onward
                         Roll out of technologies such as high yielding clones, furnace type lumber dryer,
                          engineered bamboo
                         Development of high value products

               E.  Natural Resources and Environment R&D Agenda
                    1.  Sustainable utilization, conservation and management of biodiversity in terrestrial,
                        forestry and marine ecosystems
                    2.  Sustainable watershed management and utilization
                    3.  Management and rehabilitation of problem, degraded and polluted agricultural
                        soils through remediation
                    4.  Development of high value products from agricultural and forest wastes
                    5.  Strategies/decision management tools for climate change resilient environment
                    6.  Resource and ecosystems assessment and monitoring
                    7.  Habitat management for fishery and ecosystem sustainability




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  30]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[8.  Marine environmental management (to include Harmful Algal Blooms, coastal
                        integrity/erosion, fish kills and eutrophication)
                    9.  Innovative management systems for unique landscapes and ecosystems

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Germplasm conservation of endangered plants
                         Development of molecular tools for characterizing harmful algal blooms (HABs),
                          including modelling techniques for prediction/mitigation of HABs
                         Molecular and phylogenetic studies of marine resources
                         Propagation techniques for economically important species

                         Economic valuation and accounting of biodiversity
                         Community-based ecotourism projects
                         Development of biodiversity products
                         Adoption of community-based management protocols in watershed monitoring
                         Nuclear studies on corals and marine ecosystem and resources
                         Deep resource assessment and monitoring
                         Oceanographic and connectivity studies, renewable energy studies and coastal
                          erosion and bathymetric studies

                   Priorities for 2020 onward
                         Propagation of economically important plants
                         Promotion of livelihood and ecotourism for sustainable watershed management
                         Purification of toxins from HAB-selected organisms
                         Promotion of community-based PES modules/protocols in selected watersheds
                         Pilot testing of biodiversity products
                         Proteomic studies on HABs
                         New detection and monitoring techniques for HABs
                         Development of early warning systems
                         Roll out of technologies

               F.  Climate Change Adaptation and Disaster Risk Reduction
                    1.  Mitigation and adaptation studies (including protected agriculture, vertical
                        agriculture)
                    2.  Development of smart farming approaches (including organic agriculture,
                        integrated farming, ICT application) and other climate-resilient agricultural
                        production technologies
                    3.  Development of strategies/decision management tools for climate change resilient
                        environment (e.g. farm diversification)
                    4.  Enhancing sustainable development through lifescape-landscape approach

                   Priorities for 2018-2019
                         Development of decision support systems for selected ecosystems
                         Rehabilitation strategies for critical mangrove and coastal forest




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  31]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[  Monitoring and detection of ecosystem changes

                   Priorities for 2018 onward
                         Rehabilitation of vulnerable ecosystem to climate change

                         Enhancement of resiliency of communities


               G.  Technology Transfer
                   1.  Development of innovative and improvement of traditional extension modalities for
                       the efficient transfer of technologies to end-users
                   2.  Upscaling of agricultural technology transfer and commercialization

               H.  Socio-Economics and Policy Research
                   1.  Continuing review of existing policies affecting the AANR sectors
                   2.  Policy research on natural resources/environment-related issues, agricultural trade,
                       supply chain/value chain related issues and R&D governance, compliance to
                       standards across the value chain
                   3.  Impact assessment of technologies, AANR programs and projects
                   4.  Socio-economic studies on production and marketing efficiencies, role of social
                       institutions in technology adoption, labor migration, development of social
                       enterprise models, gender and development
                   5.  Agriculture and resource economic studies including market research, agrarian/asset
                       reform, environmental valuation, economies of scale/collective farming
                   6.  Policy studies on global competitiveness of Philippines AANR sector




               The AANR ISP Roadmaps are on pages 53-75.
               For details, visit http://www.pcaarrd.dost.gov.ph/home/portal/























                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  32]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[SECTION IV



                   INDUSTRY, ENERGY AND EMERGING TECHNOLOGY

                                Research and Development Agenda

                                                   2017 – 2022



               Seventeen sectors covering various industries, the energy and transportation sectors, and
               high  impact  fields  like  biotechnology  and  nanotechnology  are  within  the  purview  of  the
               Philippine Council for Industry, Energy and Emerging Technology Research and Development
               (PCIEERD-DOST). The overarching objective of DOST-PCIEERD is to strengthen these sectors
               through  research  and  development  (R&D)  support,  human  resource  and  institution
               development, information and technology diffusion, and development of enabling policies.
               These programs contribute to the Department of Trade and Industry’s strategy of promoting
               industry  competitiveness  -  to  sustain  the  tremendous  growth  in  the  services  and
               manufacturing  sectors  experienced  over  the  last  six  years  as  well  as  develop  business
               opportunities in frontier sectors. Such goals are anchored on the Government’s long term
               goal of attaining genuine and inclusive growth.

               The  Harmonized  National  R&D  Agenda  (HNRDA)  for the  Industry  Sector  for  2017-2022  is
               formulated  through  targeted  consultations  with  the  private  sector,  National  Government
               Agencies (NGAs) and the academe. This was presented during the National R&D Conference
               in 2016 and finalized in February 2017. The foundation of the HNRDA are the consolidated
               individual DOST-PCIEERD sectoral R&D roadmaps which were crafted through a consultative
               process  with  key  stakeholders  and  aligned  with  NGA  priorities.  To  ensure  its  continued
               relevance with rapid technological changes and an increasingly globalized economy, each
               R&D roadmap is periodically assessed and updated during the period 2017-2022.

               To  secure  a  truly  harmonized  R&D  strategy  within  government,  the  DOST-PCIEERD  has
               entered  into  several  memorandum  of  agreement  with  NGAs  essentially  to  seamlessly
               integrate  R&D  efforts  strategically  and  even  fiscally  (through  co-implementation  and  co-
               funding of projects). By mid-2017, partnerships would have been forged with more than a
               dozen NGAs including the Department of Energy, Department of Public Works and Highways
               and Department of National Defense.

               Industry competitiveness will focus on micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs) and
               much  effort  will  be  provided  toward  countryside  development.  Many  R&D  projects  will
               leverage on existing resources and focus on waste utilization, value-addition of traditional
               products and efficient manufacturing processes. Lastly, it is noteworthy that four new fields
               of  research  are  to  be  included  as  priority  areas  for  2017-2022.  These  are  deemed  to  be
               emerging industries and critical to national development.
                   •  Space Technology Applications
                   •  Artificial Intelligence and Data Science
                   •  Human Security and Defense Research
                   •  Creative Industries



                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  33]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[RESEARCH PRIORITIES for INDUSTRY, ENERGY AND EMERGING TECHNOLOGY


                       A.  Food and Nutrition Security
                          Nutritious, safe and affordable food for all, at all times
                       B.  Countryside Development
                          More micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs) developing and producing
                          competitive and world class products and services
                       C.  Competitive Industry
                          More industries enabled by state-of-the-art R&D, technologies and science-
                          based policies, moving up the value chain and attracting foreign direct
                          investments
                       D.  Delivery of Social Services
                          Innovative, accessible, affordable and efficient social services for all
                       E.  Intelligent Transportation Solutions
                       F.  Renewable Energy and Energy Storage Solutions
                       G.  Human Security
                          Protection of the country and its citizens against national threats

               A. Food and Nutrition Security


                   1.  Food Safety and Quality
                       a.  Affordable Tests for Food Contaminants
                            Rapid test kits, electronic sensors for common food contaminants
                              (Microbiological contaminants, Histamine)
                            Migration test kit for various food packaging materials (paper and plastic)
                       b.  Development of Food Safety Rating and Grading System for Food Service
                          Establishments
                       c.  Safe and Regulatory-Compliant Food Products and Processes
                       d.  Improvement of Food Shelf-life
                       e.  Innovative Food Products

                     Priorities for 2018
                         Baseline Studies on Microbiological and Chemical Hazards on Food
                         Science-Based Quality Assurance System for Priority Products (e.g. fresh and
                          processed banana)
                         Value-adding of Fishery By-Products (e.g. fish oil, chitin, collagen)

               B.  Countryside Development

                   1.  Agro-Processing, Utilization and Value-Adding
                   2.  Natural Products Development
                   3.  Improvement of Textile Processing
                   4.  Halal Processing Technologies for Food and Non-Food





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  34]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[5.  Metrology and Testing Methods for Laboratory Analysis
                   6.  Shop Floor R&D and Innovations
                   7.  Regional Consortia R&D

               C.  Competitive Industries


                   1.  ICT, Electronics and Semiconductor
                       a.  Big Data Analytics
                       b.  Artificial Intelligence
                       c.  Internet of Things
                       d.  Advanced Electronics and Communications (e.g. photonics & opto-electronics
                          devices, semiconductor materials, etc.)

                       Priorities for 2018
                          Artificial Intelligence for Industry, Transport, and Education Application
                          Big Data Analytics (Government Data Integration)
                          R&D for Creative Industries

                   2.  Mining and Minerals - Technologies and processes for small and large scale mining in
                       support to responsible mining
                       a.  Green Mining Technology
                       b.  Clean Metallurgical Processes

                       Priorities for 2018
                          Development of Value-Adding Technologies for Copper, Iron, Chromite, Nickel,
                            Chromium and Gold Minerals for Industrial Application
                          Geological Assessment of Untapped/Undiscovered Minerals (i.e. Black Sand
                            and Trace and Rare Earth Elements)
                          Green Mining Technologies
                          Clean Metallurgical Processes
                            o  Hydrometallurgical
                            o  Pyrometallurgical
                            o  Electrometallurgical

                   3.  Metals and Engineering
                       a.  Advanced Machine-Based or Machine Aided Metalworking and Testing
                          Procedures
                       b.  Technologies for Disposal, Recycling, and Treatment of Metal Wastes

                       Priorities for 2018
                          Cost Efficient Manufacturing Processes and Equipment to Increase Local Content
                           of Aerospace, Automotive and/or Train Parts and Components
                          Design, Development and Prototyping of Food Processing Equipment for MSMEs







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  35]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[4.  Construction
                       a.  New Construction Materials and Techniques

                   5.  Packaging
                       a.  Smart and Green Packaging Technology
                       b.  Appropriate Packaging System for Various Products

                   6.  Industrial Application of Nuclear Technology
                       a.  Food and Non-Food Processing
                       b.  Non-Destructive Testing
                       c.  Product Development
                       d.  Environment Monitoring

               D.  Delivery of Social Services


                    1.  Environment and Pollution Control
                        a.  Wastewater Management
                               Cleaner and safer technologies for application to industrial wastewater,
                                 waste management, safe and potable drinking water, and other pressing
                                 environmental problems
                               Field-testing/application of cleaner technologies for the benefit of the
                                 industry, domestic households and general public
                               Materials that detoxify harmful substances in water
                               Removal and decomposition of spill contaminants and heavy metals
                               Mineralization of pollutants
                               Potable water
                               Storm water and storage and rainwater technologies
                               Waste Water Remediation
                               Materials and processes for desalination
                               Alternative materials and processes that will reduce or eliminate
                                 hazardous substances in the environment and manufacturing sites
                               New wastewater purification technologies and reuse of wastewater
                                 purification technologies and wastewater treatment/rehabilitation
                                 technologies
                               Treatment, control, and monitoring sensors and systems
                        b.  Air Pollution Control and Management
                               Reduction of risks of H2S emission in the environmental and industrial
                                 sectors
                               Emission reduction focusing on efficient and clean technologies
                               H2S gas sensor
                               Spatial data acquisition and management technologies (i.e. Tempospatial
                                 Distribution of atmospheric particles (Transboundary)
                               Nuclear techniques for air pollution monitoring





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  36]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[  Zeolite/bentonite applications in pollution control and mitigation
                               Alternative anti-pollutant agents

                               Development of optical techniques for air quality monitoring
                               Development of sensors for air quality monitoring
                        c.  Solid Waste Management
                               Impact on emission of pollution from solid waste
                               New product development from solid waste Solid waste minimization

                       Priorities for 2018
                          Water Environment R&D
                            o  Wastewater Management
                          Air Quality R&D
                            o  Air Pollution Control and Management
                          Solid Waste Management
                          DRR/CCA Proofing Infrastructure Systems and Techniques
                            o  Urban infrastructure rainfall inflow-outflow modeling and early warning
                                systems
                          Hazards and Risk Assessment Tools and Systems Program
                            o  Liquefaction Hazard Assessment
                          Instrumentation for early warning, monitoring and rapid assessment
                            o  Forecast Based Financing and Weather Based Insurance Mechanism
                          Marine Geology and Oceanography Program
                          Human Security
                          R&D for Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAV), Airborne and Space Technology

                   2.  Space Technology Application (STA)
                       a.  Development of micro-satellites and space technologies
                       b.  Use of STA for resource mapping
                       c.  Application of global navigation satellite system (GNSS)
                       d.  Airborne and UAV systems for high resolution mapping and other applications

               E.  Intelligent Transport Solutions

                   1.  Alternative Mass Transport Systems and Components
                       a.  Land Transport - Develop a sustainable integrated, responsive, effective, efficient
                          and safe land transport systems
                            Cost-effective alternative mass transport systems and components
                            Intelligent vehicle-to-vehicle connectivity and information sharing of speed,
                              lane changing and potential intersection crash warning data for safe vehicle
                              driving
                            Digital infrastructure needs assessment for internet of vehicles
                              implementation
                            Development of ITS control system
                            Expert system for pavement, rail management




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  37]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[  Development of traffic data collection system utilizing CCTV
                       b.  Sea/Water Transport - Develop a safer, cleaner and efficient maritime transport
                          systems and services
                            Cost-effective sea-worthy hull design using alternative lightweight materials
                              for passenger and fishing vessels and standard model design
                            Low carbon and improving energy efficiency of water craft, e.g. vessel design
                              and sea craft

                            Managing maritime traffic and safety systems, such as development localized
                              prototyped automatic identification system (AIS)

                   2.  Traffic/Mobility
                       a.  Intelligent Transport Systems
                            Commuters and public utility vehicle information systems

                            Intermodal and traffic simulation modeling tools
                            Automated traffic monitoring, violation detection, public utility vehicle (PUV)
                              tracking and safety signaling systems
                            Traffic signalization mechanization system
                       b.  Other Modes of Mobility
                            Unmanned aerial/sea surface vehicle for logistics delivery and humanitarian
                              assistance

                       Priorities for 2018
                          Intelligent Transport System
                          o  Vehicle-to-vehicle connectivity and information sharing
                          o  Road infrastructure-to-vehicle
                          o  Automated Parking Space Detection System
                          o  Harmonized radio frequency identification (RFID)/wireless sensor network
                              (WSN) using multi-path transmission protocol & cognitive frequency
                          o  PUV tracking for fleet management & driving behavior
                          Sea Transport Research on Marine Vessels
                          o  Standard sea-worthy hull design using alternative indigenous lightweight
                              materials
                          o  Navigational Route Capacity Measurement & Analysis for inter-island
                              connectivity
                         Mass Transport Systems (Train, PUV)
                          o  Prototype double decker bus development and fuel efficiency analysis in
                              compliance to Euro 4 Standards
                          o  Development of Positive Train Control (PTC) components for railway system

               F.  Renewable Energy and Energy Storage Solutions

                   1.  Energy Efficiency/Alternative Fuels and Conservation
                       a.  Energy-efficient technologies for industry and buildings
                       b.  Standards development





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  38]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[2.  Renewable Energy (RE) Systems & Bioenergy Technologies -Increase the adaptation
                       and adoption of renewable energy systems
                       a.  Cost-effective RE technologies and business models integration for sustainable off-
                          grid power supply
                       b.  Efficient micro-hydro and hydrokinetic turbines
                       c.  Bioenergy technologies
                       d.  Wind energy
                       e.  Solar power concentrators (SCP)
                       f.  Solar heating and cooling (SHC)
                   3.  Functional materials for alternative energy sources and energy conversion and storage
                       - Systems and processes for surface modification of various materials
                       a.  Superconducting  wires,  liquid  electrode  material  systems,  superconducting
                          transformers
                       b.  Cost competitive solar cells
                       c.  Platinum - and palladium - based anode catalyst for direct ethanol fuel cell
                       d.  Direct ethanol fuel cell-powered LED emergency light

                       Priorities for 2018
                         Smart Energy Efficient Systems for Low Carbon Economy
                          o   Efficient hydrokinetic energy harvesting systems
                          o   Sustainable urban waste to energy conversion
                         Renewable Energy (RE) Systems
                          o  RE technologies and business models integration for sustainable off-grid
                              power supply
                          o  Thermo/electro/biochemical hydrogen production
                          o  Solar power concentrators (SPC)
                          o  Solar heating and cooling (SHC)

               G. Human Security
                   1.  Food Defense
                   2.  Biosecurity
                   3.  Cybersecurity


               Industry, Energy and Emergency Technology Roadmaps are on pages 76-87.
               For details, visit http://pcieerd.dost.gov.ph/












                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  39]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[SECTION V



                                  DISASTER RISK REDUCTION AND

                        CLIMATE CHANGE ADAPTATION (DRR & CCA)


                               Research and Development Agenda

                                                   2017 – 2022



               The 2017-2022 Harmonized National Research and Development Agenda for Disaster Risk
               Reduction  and  Climate  Change  Adaptation  (HNRDA  DRR-CCA)  represents  the  priorities  of
               government organizations and stakeholders involved in DRR and CCA, consistent with related
               local and international development initiatives.

               The HNRDA DRR-CCA consolidates the priorities of the DOST Sectoral Councils, which have
               conducted  multi-sectoral  consultations,  DOST  agencies  and  DOST  regional  offices.  The
               research priorities were evaluated and harmonized by a team from the Philippine Institute of
               Volcanology  and  Seismology  (PHIVOLCS)  and  Philippine  Atmospheric  Geophysical  and
               Astronomical Services Administration (PAGASA) with reference to related national plans, such
               as the National Disaster Risk Reduction and Management Plan, the National Climate Change
               Action Plan, and global initiatives such as the Sustainable Development Goals and Sendai
               Framework  for  Disaster  Risk  Reduction.  Disaster  Risk  Reduction  and  Climate  Change
               Adaptation are cross-cutting concerns in the health, agriculture, environment, energy and
               industry sectors.

               The 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development was adopted by the United Nations (UN)
               General Assembly in September 2015. It sets out 17 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs)
               with  169  associated  targets  and  describes  a  number  of  international  mechanisms  for
               supporting implementation.

               DOST supports the Agenda by focusing substantial efforts to contribute to Goals 9, 11 and 13.
                       Goal 9. Build resilient infrastructure, promote inclusive and sustainable
                              industrialization and foster innovation
                       Goal 11. Make cities and human settlements inclusive, safe, resilient and sustainable
                       Goal 13. Take urgent action to combat climate change and its impacts












                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  40]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT GOALS















               The Sendai Framework for Disaster Risk Reduction (2015-2030) addresses “the risk of small-
               scale and large-scale, frequent and infrequent, sudden and slow-onset disasters, caused by
               natural or manmade hazards as well as related environmental, technological and biological
               hazards and risks. It considers climate change as one of the drivers of risk. It aims to guide the
               multi-hazard management of disaster risk in development at all levels as well as within and
               across all sectors.

               DOST supports the Framework by subscribing to the Four Priorities for Action it identified,
               namely:
                       Priority 1. Understanding disaster risk
                       Priority 2. Strengthening disaster risk governance to manage disaster risk
                       Priority 3. Investing in disaster risk reduction for resilience
                       Priority 4. Enhancing disaster preparedness for effective response, and to “Build Back
                              Better” in recovery, rehabilitation and reconstruction


                                         Sendai Framework on DRR (2015-2030)














                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  41]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[The research priorities in the agenda are organized into topics that address the four major
               action themes for Disaster Risk Reduction and Management:
                     Monitoring  and  Forecasting  (Observation  and  Monitoring  Networks,  Technology
                       Development  and  Application  for  Monitoring,  Modelling  and  Simulation  for
                       Improvement of Monitoring and Forecasting)
                     Hazard and Risk Assessment (Hazards, Vulnerability and Risk Assessment)
                     Warning (Warning and Risk Communication)
                     Proper and Timely Response (Technology Development and Application for Climate
                       Change  Mitigation  and  Adaptation,  Technology  Development  and  Application  for
                       Disaster Risk Management, and Policy Research).


                              RESEARCH PRIORITIES for DISASTER RISK REDUCTION
                                  and CLIMATE CHANGE ADAPTATION (DRR CCA)

                   A.  Observation and Monitoring Networks
                   B.  Technology Development and Application for Monitoring
                   C.  Modelling and Simulation for Improvement of Monitoring and Forecasting
                   D.  Hazards, Vulnerability and Risk Assessment
                   E.  Warning and Risk Communication
                   F.  Technology Development and Application for Climate Change Mitigation and
                       Adaptation
                   G.  Technology Development and Application for Disaster Risk Management
                   H.  Policy Research

               Priorities for 2017 onwards (Items A. to E.)
                   A. Observation and Monitoring Networks – Development of state-of-the art
                       observation and monitoring systems for weather, climate, geologic and
                       oceanographic processes.
                       1.  Weather/Climate Observation Systems
                       2.  Hydro-meteorological systems
                       3.  Ocean observation systems (including storm surges, waves)
                       4.  Volcano (seismic, geodetic, geochemical)
                       5.  Earthquake (seismic, intensity meter, accelerometers)
                       6.  Tsunami
                       7.  Landslide
                       8.  Sensor networks
                       9.  Space Systems and Facilities
                          a.  Small satellite technology
                          b.  High- to fine-resolution, multi- and hyperspectral sensor payloads
                          c.  Synthetic Aperture Radar
                          d.  Integration and Testing Facility
                          e.  Ground control stations





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  42]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[B.  Technology Development and Application for Monitoring – Development
                       of instruments and data processing and analysis systems, application of technologies
                       for improved monitoring of weather, climate, geologic and oceanographic processes.
                       1.  Hydro-meteorological and oceanographic Instruments
                       2.  Volcano, earthquake, tsunami and landslide monitoring instruments
                       3.  Instrument test bed facilities
                       4.  Radar data processing technologies
                       5.  LiDAR data processing technologies
                       6.  Remote sensing (airborne, space) technologies
                       7.  Data Assimilation System for in-situ and remotely-sensed data

                   C.  Modelling and Simulation for Improvement of Monitoring and

                       Forecasting – Modelling and simulation for improved forecasting and simulation of
                       disaster and climate scenarios.
                       1.  Numerical Weather, Sub-seasonal and Seasonal Climate Prediction, Climate
                          Change Projection
                       2.  Quantitative Precipitation Forecasting (QPF) using Numerical Weather Prediction
                          Models
                       3.  High-Impact Weather (HIW) Forecasting and Warning
                       4.  Projecting future 1.0°C and 1.5°C Philippine climate using Regional Climate
                          Models and their impacts to different sectors (Health, Food security, Water
                          resources, etc.)
                       5.  Data analytics and predictive modelling for flood monitoring and management
                       6.  Geophysical, Geochemical, Geodetic, and related modelling and simulation for
                          geological hazards monitoring and warning
                       7.  Potential for large-scale eruptions, earthquake, tsunami and landslide generation

                   D. Hazards, Vulnerability and Risk Assessment – Assessment of hazards,
                       development and update of exposure data base, assessment of vulnerabilities of
                       exposed elements such as communities and specific sectors, structures, livelihood
                       and economy, and potential impacts and losses due to natural disasters and climate
                       change; development of appropriate tools for hazard, vulnerability and risk
                       assessment.
                       1.  Hazards Assessment (Geological, Hydro-meteorological, Climate-related, etc.)
                       2.  Exposure Information, Database and Tools
                       3.  Vulnerability, Capacity and Risk Assessment
                       4.  Climate Risk (by sector)
                          a.  DRR/CCA for Agriculture (vulnerability to food insecurity, diversified farming,
                              livelihood, impact assessments, food resiliency in emergencies, etc.)
                          b.  Climate Resiliency of highly vulnerable groups and communities (women,
                              fisher folks, Indigenous People, coastal communities, etc.)







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  43]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[E.  Warning and Communication of Information – Development and use of
                       warning and information systems and protocols, determination of stakeholder
                       information needs, for improved warning and communication of information of
                       impending hazardous events and impacts for appropriate preparedness and
                       response.
                       1.  Warning Communication (Geological, Hydro-meteorological, Climate-related
                          hazards, and Impacts)
                       2.  Impact-based/risk-based modelling and forecasting
                       3.  Philippine Unified Meteo-Hydrological Information System
                       4.  Web-based and Mobile phone-based warning and information
                       5.  Geological Disaster Information Portal
                       6.  Risk communication
                       7.  Community traditional media systems
                          a.  Expansion of lexical domain (i.e. IEC materials)
                          b.  Indigenous knowledge systems and practices
                       8.  Communicating uncertainties of climate change projections for DRR/ CCA

               Priorities for 2018 onwards (Items F. to H.)
                    F.  Technology Development and Application for Climate Change

                        Mitigation and Adaptation – Development and application of instruments,
                        tools, systems, protocols to mitigate climate change by reducing greenhouse gas
                        emissions and to adapt to climate change in all sectors, including food, water,
                        health, environment, businesses, infrastructure and settlement towards a climate
                        change resilient society.
                       1.  Reduction of Greenhouse Gases Emissions
                       2.  Bio-Fuel from Forest Residues
                       3.  Energy-efficient products, Non-fossil fuels
                       4.  Microbial Biotechnology for Sustainable Waste Management and Alternative
                          Energy Source
                       5.  Resource efficient and cleaner production for industries
                       6.  Advanced Transport
                       7.  Food, Water, Health Security
                       8.  Decision management tools for climate change-resilient environment

                    G.  Technology Development and Application for Disaster Risk
                        Management – Assessment of people’s hazards, climate change and disaster risk
                        perception, gaps and needs and development and application of appropriate
                        options for risk management, development and application of instruments, tools,
                        protocols, and products in all the phases of risk management, from preparedness,
                        mitigation, response and recovery.
                        1.  Stakeholders-needs and disaster-information gap assessment and bridging for
                            disaster
                        2.  Hazards and risk perception or behavior




                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  44]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[3.  Institutional or social preparedness and response
                        4.  Projections and impact scenarios for preparedness to respond and recover
                        5.  Interactive and dynamic platform for products and services
                        6.  Tools (including software) for mainstreaming DRR-CCA into contingency
                            planning and local development and planning process
                        7.  Technologies and products for disaster mitigation (disaster-prone) and
                            recovery(disaster-stricken) of communities
                        8.  Technologies for addressing drought (i.e. cloud seeding)
                        9.  Climate and disaster resilient infrastructure
                        10. Climate and disaster resilient livelihood / business (business continuity)
                        11. Gender equality and integration in science and technology for DRR and CCA
                            partnership

                    H.  Policy Research – Development of policies for climate mitigation and adaptation
                        and disaster risk management
                        1.  Policy research for Climate Change Mitigation and Adaptation
                        2.  Policy research for Disaster Risk Management



               For details, visit http://www.phivolcs.dost.gov.ph/
                                            http://www.pagasa.dost.gov.ph/

























                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  45]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[ANNEXES: Roadmaps



































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  46]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[ANNEX 1
                                                                                       NIBRA Roadmaps













































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  47]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[ANNEX 2
                                                                                       NIBRA Roadmaps












































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  48]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[ANNEX 3
                                                                                       NIBRA Roadmaps













































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  49]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[ANNEX 4
                                                                                       NIBRA Roadmaps













































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  50]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[ANNEX 5 - NUHRA

               NATIONAL UNIFIED
               HEALTH RESEARCH AGENDA 2017-2022

               The research priorities in the National Unified Health Research Agenda (NUHRA) 2017-2022
               are subdivided into six themes with several areas as follows:

                     Theme 1. Responsive health systems

                     Health governance
                     Health financing
                     Access to essential medical products, vaccines and technologies
                     Health information systems
                     Health service delivery
                     Health human resource
                     Health economics
                     Health research management

                     Theme 2. Research to enhance and extend healthy lives

                     Adolescent health
                     Communicable diseases
                     Environmental health
                     Maternal, newborn and child health
                     Mental health
                     Non communicable diseases
                     Nutrition
                     Oral health
                     Reproductive health

                     Theme 3. Holistic approaches to health and wellness

                     Filipino traditional and complementary medicine
                     Determinants of health
                     Halal in health
                     Health behaviors

                     Theme 4. Health resiliency

                     Accidents and injuries
                     Climate change
                     Disaster risk reduction
                     Emerging and re-emerging diseases
                     Environmental threats
                     Migration and health
                     Occupational health





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  51]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[NATIONAL UNIFIED
               HEALTH RESEARCH AGENDA 2017-2022

                     Theme 5. Global competitiveness and innovation in health

                     Diagnostics
                     Drug discovery and development
                     Functional foods
                     Information and Communication Technologies for Health
                     Biomedical products
                     Omic technologies for health

                     Theme 6. Equity in health research

                     Disability
                     Gender
                     Geriatric care
                     Geographically isolated and disadvantaged areas
                     Indigenous peoples
                     Substance abuse
                     Violence

                 The new NUHRA  document  is being  finalized  and  will  be  available in  August 2017.  It  is
                 planned to be launched during the PNHRS Week to be celebrated in the same month.

























                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  52]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[ANNEX 6
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               CROPS







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  53]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[ANNEX 7
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               CROPS







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  54]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[ANNEX 8
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               CROPS:  LEGUMES






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  55]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[ANNEX 9
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               CROPS







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  56]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[ANNEX 10
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               CROPS:  ROOTCROPS

































               CROPS








































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  57]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[ANNEX 11
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               CROPS:  TROPICAL FRUITS






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  58]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[ANNEX 12
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               CROPS:  TROPICAL FRUITS

               The R&D Roadmap for papaya covers the period 2017-2021. Stakeholders for this product will be
               consulted for the next initiatives/plans.





































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  59]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[ANNEX 13
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               CROPS:  TROPICAL FRUITS



































               CROPS



































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  60]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[ANNEX 14
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               LIVESTOCK







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  61]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[ANNEX 15
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               LIVESTOCK






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  62]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[ANNEX 16
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               LIVESTOCK








































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  63]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[ANNEX 17
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               LIVESTOCK







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  64]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[ANNEX 18
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               AQUATIC:  INLAND





































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  65]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[ANNEX 19
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               AQUATIC:  INLAND







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  66]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[ANNEX 20
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               AQUATIC:  INLAND







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  67]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[ANNEX 21
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               AQUATIC:  MARINE


               The R&D Roadmap for Abalone covers the period 2017-2021 only as the initiatives for abalone is
               already complete by 2021.



































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  68]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[ANNEX 22
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               AQUATIC:  MARINE





































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  69]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[ANNEX 23
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               AQUATIC:  MARINE






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  70]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[ANNEX 24
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps


               AQUATIC:  MARINE


               The  R&D  Roadmap  for  tuna  covers  the  period  2017-2021.  Stakeholders  for  this  product  will  be
               consulted for the next initiatives/plans.
































               FORESTRY AND NATURAL RESOURCES


































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  71]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[ANNEX 25
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               FORESTRY AND NATURAL RESOURCES






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  72]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[ANNEX 26
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps

               FORESTRY AND NATURAL RESOURCES































               ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES










































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  73]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[ANNEX 27
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                       Roadmaps



               ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES






































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  74]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[ANNEX 28
                                                                                AANR Programs/Projects
                                                                                        Roadmaps


               ENVIRONMENTAL SERVICES







































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  75]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[ANNEX 29 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               Most of the roadmaps of the industry, energy and emerging sectors cover the period 2013-
               2017.   Since  these  are  updated  every  5  years,   PCIEERD  is  currently  updating  its  sectoral
               roadmaps  for  2018-2022  through  stakeholders'  consultations  and  is  expected  to  be
               completed before the end of 2017.


               COMPETITIVE INDUSTRIES:

               ICT, ELECTRONICS AND SEMICONDUCTOR

       Technology    Areas /        2014                  2015                     2016               2017    2018
         Cluster    Discipline
       Ubiquitous /   Sensors,    Empathic Space for    Empathic Space v2.0 for    Security APIs for
       Pervasive   Embedded    Stroke Patients   Persons Afflicted with Autism   Mobile/Handheld Devices
       Computing   Systems,
                   Robotics,   Developing       Developing Technology-based   Security Mechanisms for Mobile
                   Security,   Technology-based   Support Tools for Children with   Devices
                   Image/Video   Therapies for Stroke   Autism (Dr. Suarez)   (Dr. Festin)
                   Retrieval, Next   Patients (Dr. Suarez)
                   Generation
                   Network
                                 Vision-Based     Security APIs for        Collaborative control systems for
                               Vehicle Counting   Mobile/Handheld Devices   multiple UAVs surveying a
                               System and Traffic                        geographical Area
                               Emissions Inventory
                               Vision-based Vehicle   Security Mechanisms for Mobile   Aerial Dynamic Assessment Robot
                               Counter for Emissions   Devices           for National Advancement           -
                               Inventory and Traffic   (Dr. Festin)      phase III
                               Monitoring (VIVEC-                        (Dr. Suarez)
                               ET) (Dr. Suarez)

                                                  Unmanned Aerial Vehicle
                                                System (UAV) for Surveillance
                                                Operations

                                                Aerial Dynamic Assessment Robot
                                                for National Advancement
                                                – phase II
                                                (Dr. Suarez)

       Human       Empathic,     Embodied         Embodied Conversational    Computer Storytellers in an ILE
       Machine     Affective, NLP,   Conversational   Agents Interacting with Persons   to Motivate Learners
       Interaction   Speech    Agents Teaching   Afflicted with Autism
                   Recognition,   English

                   Machine     Teaching English as a   Developing Technology-based    Exploring Stories as Tools to
                   Vision,     Second Language   Support Tools for Children with   Influence the Emotion of Learners
                   Machine     using ECAs (Dr.   Autism (Dr. Suarez)     (Dr. Suarez)
                   Intelligence   Suarez)

                                 An Affect Model of    Software Tutors for Gifted
                               Readers in an ILE for   Children
                               Reading

                               Building an Affect   Developing Empathic Educational
                               Model of Student
                               Readers as they
                               Read Story Text (Dr.
                               Suarez)










                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  76]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[ANNEX 30 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps


               COMPETITIVE INDUSTRIES:

               ICT, ELECTRONICS AND SEMICONDUCTOR

       Technology   Areas / Discipline   2014             2015                      2016              2017    2018
         Cluster
                                  Alex: A         Interactive Storytelling
                                Collaborative Peer in   Environment to promote Maternal
                                an Interactive   Health Awareness
                                Storytelling
                                Environment for
                                Disaster
                                Preparedness

                                Supporting Behavior Awareness through Interactive Social
                                Stories (Dr. Suarez)

                                                  Embodied Conversational Agent
                                                interacting with Readers in an ILE for
                                                Reading

                                                Integrating an Embodied
                                                Conversational Agent into an ILE for
                                                Reading (Dr. Suarez)

                                                  Development of low cost research    Data gathering in various contexts,    Data
                                                platforms that can assess user   e.g. film, advertising, driving, learning   analysis
                                                engagement, boredom, confusion                       Report
                                                based on posture, eye-gaze and                     writing
                                                biometrics                                           Publication

                                                Development of low-cost research platforms for assessing user affect (Dr. Rodrigo)

       Computationa  Grid, Cloud,                 Algorithms for Secure Data Mining    Algorithms for Secure Data Mining
       l Systems and   Modeling &
       Services   Simulation,                   Algorithms for Secure Data Mining (Dr. Festin)
                  Visualization,
                  Datamining ,
                  Analytics

       Digital Media   Games, Animation,    Mobile Picture    Animated Picture Books    Intelligent Tutoring Game System
       and Creative   Digital Lib, E-   Books
       Content    learning/Instruction
                  al Systems,   Story Generation Systems as Support Tools for Literacy   Development of intelligent tutoring
                  Entertainment   Development in Children (Dr. Suarez)   systems for Araling Panlipunan and
                  Computing,                                             Filipino for middle school (Dr. Rodrigo)
                  Image/Video
                  Processing

       Web Science   Web Semantics,
                  Q&A on the Web,
                  Social Networking,
                  Ontologies,
                  Internet of Things

       Foundation of   Algorithms,                Algorithms for Secure Data Mining    Algorithms for Secure Data Mining
       Computer   Systems Software,             v.1.0                    v.2.0
       Science    Languages, Basic              Algorithms for Secure Data Mining (Dr. Festin)
                  Research on
                  Computer Science
                  Architecture

       ICT for    GIS, Health     Pinoy SimCity v1.0    Pinoy SimCity v2.0
       Development   Informatics,
       (Government   Instructional,   Developing an Environment for Simulating City Planning
       Thrusts –   Environment,   through Community-Based Monitoring System Data (Dr.
       usage and   Service Science   Suarez)
       applications)   (incl. Tele-health),
                  Bio-informatics, E-             Personal Health Records on    Personal Health Records on Mobile
                  governance                    Mobile Devices           Devices

                                                Personal Health Records on Mobile Devices (Dr. Festin)






                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  77]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[ANNEX 31 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps


               DELIVERY OF SOCIAL SERVICES:  DRR/CCA


















































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  78]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[ANNEX 32 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               DELIVERY OF SOCIAL SERVICES:  SPACE TECHNOLOGY APPLICATION (STA)












































                         *KDA – Key Development Area





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  79]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[ANNEX 33 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               DELIVERY OF SOCIAL SERVICES:  SPACE TECHNOLOGY APPLICATION (STA)











































                          *KDA – Key Development Area





                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  80]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[ANNEX 34 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               DELIVERY OF SOCIAL SERVICES:  SPACE TECHNOLOGY APPLICATION (STA)










































                         *KDA – Key Development Area







                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  81]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[ANNEX 35 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SOLUTIONS


















































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  82]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[ANNEX 36 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SOLUTIONS













































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  83]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[ANNEX 37 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SOLUTIONS

































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  84]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[ANNEX 38 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SOLUTIONS















































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  85]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[ANNEX 39 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps



               INTELLIGENT TRANSPORTATION SOLUTIONS





























































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  86]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[ANNEX 40 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                        Emerging Technology Roadmaps

               RENEWABLE ENERGY AND ENERGY STORAGE SOLUTIONS

















































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  87]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[ANNEX 41 - Industry, Energy and
                                                                         Emerging Technology Roadmaps


               RENEWABLE ENERGY AND ENERGY STORAGE SOLUTIONS
































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  88]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[ANNEX 42
                                                                                DRR-CCA R&D Roadmap



































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  89]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[ANNEX 43
                                                                                     PAGASA Roadmap

















































































                                                                                                                                             HNRDA 2017-2022  | Page  90]]></page></pages></Search>
